const quizQuestions = [

  {

    question: "Which of the following is generally used for performing tasks like creating the structure of the relations, deleting relation?",

    options: ["DML","Query","Relational Schema","DDL"],

    correctAnswer: "DDL"

  },

  {

    question: "Which of the following provides the ability to query information from the database and insert tuples into, delete tuples from, and modify tuples in the database?",

    options: ["DML", "DDL", "Query", "Relational Schema"],

    correctAnswer: "DML"

  },

  {
    question: " Which of the following can be considered as the maximum size that is supported by FAT?",

    options: ["8GB", "4GB", "4TB", "None of the above"],

    correctAnswer: "4GB"

  },

  {

     question: "Which of the following can be considered as the maximum size that is supported by NTFS?",

     options: ["4GB", "16TB", "64TB", "8TB"],

    correctAnswer: "4GB"

  },

  {

     question: "A huge collection of the information or data accumulated form several different sources is known as ________:",

     options: ["Data Management", "Data Mining", "Data Warehouse", "Both B and C"],

     correctAnswer: "Data Warehouse"

  },

  {

    question:"Which of the following can be used to extract or filter the data & information from the data warehouse?",

    options:["Data redundancy","Data recovery tool","Data mining","Both B and C"],

    correctAnswer:"Data mining"

  },

  {

      question:"Which one of the following refers to the copies of the same data (or information) occupying the memory space at multiple places.",

      options:["Data Repository","Data Inconsistency","Data Mining","Data Redundancy"],

      correctAnswer:"Data Redundancy"

    },

  {

    questio:"Which one of the following refers to the 'data about data'?",

      options:["Directory","Sub Data","Warehouse","Meta Data"],

      correctAnswer:"Meta Data"

    },

  {

    question:"Which of the following refers to the level of data abstraction that describes exactly how the data actually stored?",

    options:["Conceptual Level","Physical Level","File Level","Logical Level"],

       correctAnswer:"Physical Level"

     },

  {

     question:" To which of the following the term 'DBA' referred?",

    options:["Data Bank Administrator","Database Administrator","Data Administrator","None of the above"],

       correctAnswer:"Database Administrator"

    },

  {

    question:" In general, a file is basically a collection of all related______.",

    options:["Rows & Columns","Fields","Database","Records"],

    correctAnswer:"Records"

    },

  {

    question:"Rows of a relation are known as the _______.",

    options:["Degree","Tuples","Entity","All of the above"],

    correctAnswer:"All of the above"

    },

  {

    question:"Which of the following refers to the number of tuples in a relation?",

    options:["Entity","Column","Cardinality","None of the above"],

    correctAnswer:"Cardinality"

    },

  {

    question:"Which one of the following is a type of Data Manipulation Command?",

    options:["Create","char","Delete","All of the above"],

    correctAnswer:"Delete"

    },

  {

    question:"Which of the following command is a type of Data Definition language command?",

    options:["Create","Update","Delete","Merge"],

    correctAnswer:"Create"

    },

    {

        question:"Which of the following is a top-down approach in which the entity's higher level can be divided into two lower sub-entities?",

        options:["Aggregation","Generalization","Specialization","All of the above"],

        correctAnswer:"Specialization"

      },

    {

      question:" In which one of the following, the multiple lower entities are grouped (or combined) together to form a single higher-level entity?",

        options:["Specialization","Generalization","Aggregation","None of the above"],

        correctAnswer:"Generalization"

    },

    {

    question:"In a relation database, every tuples divided into the fields are known as the______.",

    options:["Queries","Domains","Relations","All of the above"],

         correctAnswer:"Domains"

      },

    {

    question:"In the relational table, which of the following can also be represented by the term 'attribute'?",

    options:["Entity","Row","Column","Both B &C"],

         correctAnswer:"Column"

      },

    {

    question:"Which of the following refers to the number of attributes in a relation?",

    options:["Degree","Row","Column","All of the above"],

    correctAnswer:"Degree"

    },

    {

    question:"Which one of the following command is used to delete the existing row in a table?",

    options:["Delete","Update","Insert","none"],

    correctAnswer:"Delete"

    },

    {

    question:"Which of the following commands is used to save any transaction permanently into the database?",

    options:["Commit","Rollback","Savepoint","None of the above"],

    correctAnswer:"Commit"

    },

    {

    question:"Which one of the following commands is used for removing (or deleting) a relation forms the SQL database?",

    options:["Delete","Drop","Remove","All of the above"],

      correctAnswer:"Delete"

    },

    {

    question:"Which one of the following commands is used to restore the database to the last committed state?",

    options:["Savepoint","Rollback","Commit","Both A & B"],

      correctAnswer:"Rollback"

      },

      {

          question:"The database management system can be considered as the collection of ______ that enables us to create and maintain the database.",

          options:["Translators","Programs","Keys","Language activity"],

          correctAnswer:"Programs"

        },

      {

        question:"The term 'DFD' stands for?",

          options:["Data file diagram","Data flow document","Data flow diagram","None of the above"],

          correctAnswer:"Data flow diagram"

      },

      {

      question:"Which of the following refers collection of the information stored in a database at a specific time?",

      options:["Independence","Instance of the database","Schema","Data domain"],

           correctAnswer:"Instance of the database"

        },

      {

      question:"Which one of the following refers to the total view of the database content?",

      options:["Conceptual view","Physical view","Internal view","External view"],

           correctAnswer:"Conceptual view"

        },

      {

      question:"The architecture of a database can be viewed as the ________",

      options:["One level","Two-level","Three-level","Four level"],

      correctAnswer:"Three-level"

      },

      {

      question:"In the relation model, the relation are generally termed as ________",

      options:["Tuples","Attributes","Rows","Tables"],

      correctAnswer:"Tables"

      },

      {

      question:"Which of the following keys is generally used to represents the relationships between the tables?",

      options:["Primary key","Foreign key","Secondary key","None of the above"],

      correctAnswer:"Foreign key"

      },

      {

      question:"Which of the following levels is considered as the level closed to the end-users?",

      options:["Internal Level","External Level","Conceptual Level","Physical Level"],

        correctAnswer:"External Level"

      },

      {

      question:"A computer security protocol for logging-in can be considered as the example of the ______ component of an information system.",

      options:["Data","Software","Procedure","Hardware"],

        correctAnswer:"Procedure"

        },

        {

            question:"Which one of the following keyword is used to find out the number of values in a column?",

            options:["TOTAL","COUNT","SUM","ADD"],

            correctAnswer:"COUNT"

          },

        {

          question:"Which one of the following commands is used to modify a column inside a table?",

            options:["Drop","Update","Alter","Set"],

            correctAnswer:"Alter"

        },

        {

        question:"Who created the first DBMS?",

        options:["Edgar Frank Codd","Charles Bachman","Charles Babbage","Sharon B. Codd"],

             correctAnswer:"Charles Bachman"

          },

        {

        question:"Which of the following is not a type of database?",

        options:["Hierarchical","Network","Distributed","Decentralized"],

             correctAnswer:"Decentralized"

          },

        {

        question:"In which of the following formats data is stored in the database management system?",

        options:["Image","Text","Table","Graph"],

        correctAnswer:"Table"

        },

        {

        question:"Which of the following is not an example of DBMS?",

        options:["MySQL","Microsoft Acess","IBM DB2","Google"],

        correctAnswer:"false"

        },

        {

        question:"Which of the following is a component of the DBMS?",

        options:["Data","Data Languages","Data Manager","All of the above"],

        correctAnswer:"All of the above"

        },

        {

        question:"Which of the following is known as a set of entities of the same type that share same properties, or attributes?",

        options:["Relation set","Tuples","Entity set","Entity Relation model"],

          correctAnswer:"Entity set"

  },

 {

    question:"What is information about data called?",

    options:["Hyper data","Tera data","Meta data","Relations"],

    correctAnswer:"Meta data"

  },

  {

  question:"The ability to query data, as well as insert, delete, and alter tuples, is offered by ____________",

  options:["TCL","DCL","DDL","DML"],

  correctAnswer:"DML"

   },

   {

   question:" ______________ is a set of one or more attributes taken collectively to uniquely identify a record.",

   options:["Primary Key","Foreign key","Super key","Candidate key"],

   correctAnswer:"Super key"

    },

    {

    question:"Which command is used to remove a relation from an SQL?",

    options:["Drop table","Delete","Purge","Remove"],

    correctAnswer:"Drop table"

     },



 {

    question:"_________________ operations do not preserve non-matched tuples.",

    options: ["Left outer join", "Inner join", "Natural join", "Right outer join"],

    correctAnswer: "Inner join"

  },

  {

    question: "After groups have been established, SQL applies predicates in the ___________ clause, allowing aggregate functions to be used.",

    options: ["Where", "Having", "Group by", "With"],

    correctAnswer: "Having"

  },

  {

     question:"Which of the following is not the utility of DBMS?",

     options: ["Backup", "Data Loading", "Process Organization", "File organization"],

     correctAnswer: "Process Organization"

  },

  {

    question:"Which of the following is the best way to represent the attributes in a large db?",

    options: ["Dot representation", "Concatenation", "Relational-and", "All of the mentioned"],

    correctAnswer: "Concatenation"

   },

   {

     question:"Which of the following functions construct histograms and use buckets for ranking?",

     options: ["Ntil()", "Newtil()", "Rank()", "All of the mentioned"],

     correctAnswer: "Ntil()"

   },

   {

      question: "Which of the following is known as the process of viewing cross-tab with a fixed value of one attribute?",

      options: ["Dicing", "Pivoting", "Slicing", "Both Pivoting and Dicing"],

      correctAnswer: "Slicing"

   },

   {

    question: "For designing a normal RDBMS which of the following normal form is considered adequate?",

    options: ["4NF", "3NF", "2NF", "5NF"],

    correctAnswer: "3NF"

   },

   {

    question: "The oldest DB model is _______________",

    options: ["Network", "Physical", "Hierarchical", "Relational"],

    correctAnswer: "Hierarchical"

   },

   {

    question: "A major goal of the db system is to minimize the number of block transfers between the disk and memory. Which of the following helps in achieving this goal??",

    options: [ "Secondary storage", "Storage","Catalog", "Buffer"],

    correctAnswer: "Buffer"

   },

   {

    question: "A view of database that appears to an application program is known as",

    options: ["Schema","Subschema","Virtual table","Index Table"],

    correctAnswer: "Subschema"

   },

   {

     question: "Which operation is used to extract specified columns from a table?",

     options: ["Project","Join","Extract","Substitute"],

     correctAnswer: "Project"

    },

   {

     question: "Relations produced from E - R Model will always be in ________.",

     options: ["1 NF","2 NF","3 NF","4 NF"],

     correctAnswer: "1 NF"

    },

    {

      question: "Consider the relation R (ABCDE): FD = { A → B, B → C, C → D, D → E} Find out the highest normal form.",

      options: ["1 NF","2 NF","3 NF","BCNF"],

      correctAnswer: "2 NF"

    },

    {

      question: "__________ rules used to limit the volume of log information that has to be handled and processed in the event of system failure involving the loss of volatile information.",

      options: ["Write-ahead log","Check-pointing","Log buffer","Thomas"],

      correctAnswer: "Check-pointing"

    },

    {

      question: "Which of the following RAID level provides the highest Data Transfer Rate (Read/Write)",

      options: ["RAID 1","RAID 3","RAID 4","RAID 5"],

      correctAnswer: "RAID 1"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which of the following is the highest isolation level in transaction management?",

      options: ["Serializable","Repeated Read","Committed Read","Uncommitted Read"],

      correctAnswer: "Serializable"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which symbol do we use in place of the except?",

      options: ["~","¬","V","^"],

      correctAnswer: "¬"

    },	
    {

      question: "What is an alternative name for a weak entity?",

      options: ["Dominant","Owner","Child","All of the above"],

      correctAnswer: "Child"

    },	
    {

      question: "The _____ system does not require a password to travel across the internet.",

      options: ["Response","Challenge-response","Manipulation","Readable"],

      correctAnswer: "Challenge-response"

    },	
    {

      question: "The Optical disk technology utilises:",

      options: ["RAID","A laser beam","DAT","Helical scanning"],

      correctAnswer: "RAID"

    },	
    {

      question: "The node pointing towards another node in a B+ tree is known as:",

      options: ["External node","Leaf node","Internal node","Final node"],

      correctAnswer: "Internal node"

    },	
    {

      question: "An operator shall provide the transaction file’s name, and the file consisting of the edited transactions (that are ready for execution) must be called:",

      options: ["Trans. Exe","Batch. Exe","Edit. Exe","Opt. Exe"],

      correctAnswer: "Opt. Exe"

    },	
    {

      question: "The name of the very first microprocessor chip available commercially was:",

      options: ["Intel 4004"," Intel 639","Intel 308","Motorola 33"],

      correctAnswer: "Intel 4004"

    },	
    {

      question: "The easiest way in which we can transfer control is when the old backup site sends __________ to the old primary.",

      options: ["Redo logs","Primary Logs","Undo Logs","All of the above"],

      correctAnswer: "Primary Logs"

    },	
    {

      question: "A linear search algorithm’s complexity would be:",

      options: ["O(n2)","O(n log n)","O(n)","O(log n)"],

      correctAnswer: "O(n)"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which of the following best defines a database?",

      options: ["A collection of programs","A type of software","A collection of data","A type of computer"],

      correctAnswer: "A collection of data"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of a DBMS?",

      options: ["Data redundancy","Data integrity","Data security","Data independence"],

      correctAnswer: "Data redundancy"

    },	
    {

      question: "The process of organizing data into tables and establishing relationships between them is known as:",

      options: ["Data mining","Data modeling","Data warehousing","Database design"],

      correctAnswer: "Database design"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which of the following SQL statements is used to insert a new record into a table?",

      options: ["SELECT","INSERT INTO","UPDATE","DELETE"],

      correctAnswer: "INSERT INTO"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which of the following is a correct syntax to select all columns from a table named 'Customers'?",

      options: ["SELECT * FROM Customers","SELECT Customers","SELECT all FROM Customers","GET * FROM Customers"],

      correctAnswer: "SELECT * FROM Customers"

    },	
    {

      question: "In an ER diagram, what do entities represent?",

      options: ["Relationships between tables","Physical storage locations","Real-world objects or concepts","Database queries"],

      correctAnswer: "Real-world objects or concepts"

    },	
    {

      question: "The uniqueness of each row in a database table is ensured by:",

      options: ["The primary key","The foreign key","An index","A trigger"],

      correctAnswer: "The primary key"

    },	
    {

      question: "A relationship in an ER model that involves more than two entity types is known as",

      options: ["A binary relationship","A ternary relationship","A primary relationship","An associative relationship"],

      correctAnswer: "A ternary relationship"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which of the following is NOT a type of integrity constraint in a relational database?",

      options: ["Referential integrity","Semantic integrity","Structural integrity","Domain integrity"],

      correctAnswer: "Structural integrity"

    },	
    {

      question: "An attribute that uniquely identifies each entity in an entity set is called a:",

      options: ["Composite attribute","Derived attribute","Multi-valued attribute","Key attribute"],

      correctAnswer: "Key attribute"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which SQL keyword is used to remove a table from a database?",

      options: ["DROP","DELETE","REMOVE","ALTER"],

      correctAnswer: "DROP"

    },	
    {

      question: "An ER diagram incorrectly shows two entities directly connected by more than one relationship.What is this error known as?",

      options: ["Relationship redundancy","Cardinality mismatch","Entity ambiguity","Attribute duplication"],

      correctAnswer: "Relationship redundancy"

    },	
    {

      question: "In an ER diagram, an entity set that does not have sufficient attributes to form a primary key is marked as:",

      options: ["Weak entity","Strong entity","Derived entity","Composite entity"],

      correctAnswer: "Weak entity"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which SQL statement is used to extract data from a database?",

      options: ["INSERT INTO","UPDATE","SELECT","DELETE"],

      correctAnswer: "SELECT"

    },
    {

      question: "An index in a database is used to:",

      options: ["Decrease storage space","Increase data redundancy","Speed up data retrieval","Secure the database"],

      correctAnswer: "Speed up data retrieval"

    },	
    {

      question: "Which SQL clause is used to filter groups of rows that have been aggregated?",

      options: ["WHERE","HAVING","GROUP BY","ORDER BY"],

      correctAnswer: "HAVING"

    },
    {

      question: "The process of minimizing redundancy and dependency by organizing fields and table relationships is known as:",

      options: ["Denormalization","Normalization","Indexing","Partitioning"],

      correctAnswer: "Normalization"

    },
    {

      question: "Which normal form is concerned with removing partial dependency between columns of a database table?",

      options: ["1NF","2NF","3NF","BCNF"],

      correctAnswer: "2NF"

    },
    {

      question: "Which SQL keyword is used to create a unique constraint on a column to enforce uniqueness?",

      options: ["UNIQUE","PRIMARY KEY","CHECK","FOREIGN KEY"],

      correctAnswer: "UNIQUE"

    },
    {

      question: "Which property of a transaction ensures that all operations within the transaction are completed successfully, or none of them are?",

      options: ["Atomicity","Consistency","Isolation","Durability"],

      correctAnswer: "Atomicity"

    },
    {

      question: "Which of the following is NOT a property of transactions (ACID properties)?",

      options: ["Authenticity","Atomicity","Consistency","Isolation"],

      correctAnswer: "Authenticity"

    },
    {

      question: "Which SQL statement is used to start a transaction in most RDBMS?",

      options: ["BEGIN TRANSACTION","START","SELECT","BEGIN"],

      correctAnswer: "BEGIN TRANSACTION"

    },
    {

      question: "Which SQL command is used to save a point within a transaction that can be rolled back to, without affecting the preceding statements of the transaction?",

      options: ["SAVEPOINT","CHECKPOINT","COMMIT TO POINT","ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT"],

      correctAnswer: "SAVEPOINT"

    },
    {

      question: "The isolation level that allows dirty reads, non-repeatable reads, and phantom reads is:",

      options: ["Read Uncommitted","Read Committed","Repeatable Read","Serializable"],

      correctAnswer: "Read Uncommitted"

    },
    {

      question: "Which of the following SQL statements is used to insert a new record into a table?",

      options: ["INSERT INTO","UPDATE","SELECT","DELETE"],

      correctAnswer: "INSERT INTO"

    },
    {

      question: "Which of the following is a correct syntax to select all columns from a table named 'Customers'?",

      options: ["SELECT * FROM Customers","SELECT Customers","SELECT all FROM Customers","GET * FROM Customers"],

      correctAnswer: "SELECT * FROM Customers"

    },
    {

      question: "The uniqueness of each row in a database table is ensured by:",

      options: ["The primary key","The foreign key","An index","A trigger"],

      correctAnswer: "The primary key"

    },
    {

      question: "Which SQL keyword is used to remove a table from a database?",

      options: ["DROP","UPDATE","SELECT","DELETE"],

      correctAnswer: "DROP"

    },
    {

      question: "Which SQL statement is used to extract data from a database?",

      options: ["INSERT INTO","UPDATE","SELECT","DELETE"],

      correctAnswer: "SELECT"

    },
    {

      question: "Which SQL clause is used to filter groups of rows that have been aggregated?",

      options: ["INSERT INTO","HAVING","SELECT","WHERE"],

      correctAnswer: "HAVING"

    },	  

];



// Variables to track quiz state

let currentQuestionIndex = 0;

let score = 0;

let timeLeft = 900; // 15 minutes in seconds

let timerInterval;

let selectedQuestions = []; // Array to hold the selected questions



// Function to start the quiz

function startQuiz() {

  // Shuffle and select 20 random questions

  selectedQuestions = shuffleArray(quizQuestions).slice(0, 20);



  // Hide the start button and display the first question

  document.getElementById("start-button").style.display = "none";

  displayQuestion();

  startTimer();

}



// Function to shuffle an array (Fisher-Yates shuffle)

function shuffleArray(array) {

  for (let i = array.length - 1; i > 0; i--) {

    const j = Math.floor(Math.random() * (i + 1));

    [array[i], array[j]] = [array[j], array[i]];

  }

  return array;

}



// Function to display a question and its options

function displayQuestion() {

  const currentQuestion = selectedQuestions[currentQuestionIndex];

  const questionText = document.getElementById("question-text");

  const answerButtons = document.getElementById("answer-buttons");



  // Clear previous question and answer options

  questionText.innerHTML = "";

  answerButtons.innerHTML = "";



  // Display the current question

  questionText.innerHTML = currentQuestion.question;



  // Create answer buttons for each option

  currentQuestion.options.forEach(option => {

    const button = document.createElement("button");

    button.innerText = option;

    button.classList.add("answer-button");

    answerButtons.appendChild(button);



    // Add click event listener to check the answer

    button.addEventListener("click", function() {

      checkAnswer(option);

    });

  });

}



// Function to check the selected answer

function checkAnswer(selectedOption) {

  const currentQuestion = selectedQuestions[currentQuestionIndex];



  // Check if the selected answer is correct

  if (selectedOption === currentQuestion.correctAnswer) {

    score++;

  }



  // Move to the next question or end the quiz if all questions are answered

  currentQuestionIndex++;



  if (currentQuestionIndex < selectedQuestions.length) {

    displayQuestion();

  } else {

    endQuiz();

  }

}



// function to start the timer

function startTimer() {

  timerInterval = setInterval(function() {

    timeLeft--;



    // Calculate minutes and seconds

    const minutes = Math.floor(timeLeft / 60);

    const seconds = timeLeft % 60;



    // Update the timer text

    document.getElementById("minutes").textContent = minutes;

    document.getElementById("seconds").textContent = seconds < 10 ? "0" + seconds : seconds;



    // End the quiz if time runs out

    if (timeLeft <= 0) {

      endQuiz();

    }

  }, 1000);

}



// Function to end the quiz

function endQuiz() {

  // Stop the timer

  clearInterval(timerInterval);



  // Calculate the score percentage

  const wrongAns = selectedQuestions.length - score;



  // Display the final score

  const questionContainer = document.getElementById("question-container");

  const resultsWindow = document.getElementById("results-window");



  let message = `

    <h2>Quiz Completed!</h2>

    <p id="question-text">Your Score       : ${score} out of ${selectedQuestions.length}</p>

    <p id="question-text">Correct Answers  : ${score}</p>

  `;



  // Check score and show modal if score is less than 5

  if (score < 5) {

    message += `<p id="question-text">Better luck next time!</p>`;

  } else {

    message += `<p id="question-text">Congratulations!</p>`;

  }



  resultsWindow.innerHTML = message;

  resultsWindow.classList.remove("hidden");

}



// Function to close the results modal

function closeResultsModal() {

  const resultsWindow = document.getElementById("results-window");

  resultsWindow.classList.add("hidden");

}



// Add event listener to start the quiz when the start button is clicked

document.getElementById("start-button").addEventListener("click", startQuiz);



// Event listener to close modal when clicking outside

window.addEventListener("click", function(event) {

  const resultsWindow = document.getElementById("results-window");

  if (event.target === resultsWindow) {

    closeResultsModal();

  }

});